A Finding Aid to the Edward Dugmore Papers, 1937-1993, in the Archives of American Art AAA.dugmedwa
Archives of American Art
Edward Dugmore papers
1937-1993
AAA.dugmedwa
Archives of American Art
2 Linear feet
The papers of painter and instructor Edward Dugmore measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1937-1993. Found within this small collection are biographical materials, scattered business and financial records, notes, a file concerning the Drake University Summer Session, printed material, and photographs. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence exchanged with art critic Hubert Crehan and artist colleagues including George Abend, Ernie Briggs, Herman Cherry, Lucien Day, Harvey Harris, Reuben Kadish, Mary Fuller McChesney, and Clyfford Still.
Edward Dugmore
Provenance
The Edward Dugmore papers were donated in several increments between 1980 to 1993 by the artist.
Related Material
Among the holdings of the Archives of American Art is a transcribed oral history interview with Edward Dugmore conducted by Tram Combs in 1994.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Edward Dugmore (1915-1996) was a painter and arts instructor working in New York, San Francisco, Illinois, and Maryland.
Edward Dugmore was born in 1915 in Hartford Connecticutt, the son of Walter and Ellen Spragg Dugmore. Dugmore received a four year scholarship to study painting at Hartford Art School from 1934 to 1938. In 1938, he also married Edith Oslund. He briefly studied lithography and etching under Thomas Hart Benton at the Kansas City (Missouri) Art Institute in 1941. After serving in the U.S. Marine Corps during World War II, he returned to New York City. From 1946 to 1948, he taught painting and drawing at St. Joseph's College in West Hartford, Connecticut.
In 1948, Dugmore moved to San Francisco and began two year's study of art under the G.I. Bill at the California School of Fine Arts, were he befriended Clyfford Still and Ernest Briggs. He co-founded the artists' collaborative Metart Gallery, where he had his first solo exhibition in 1950.
From 1951 to 1952, Dugmore studied at the University of Guadalajara, Mexico, earning a master's degree in fine arts. In 1952, he moved back to New York City where he had solo exhibitions at the Stable Gallery over the following three years. He also had solo exhibitions at the Howard Wise Gallery in New York and Cleveland during the 1960s.
Between 1961 and 1962, Dugmore was Visiting Artist at the University of Southern Illinois, and in 1970, he was Visiting Artist at the Des Moines Art Center and Drake University. From 1964 to 1974, he taught painting and drawing part time at the Pratt Institute, and in 1965, he was Artist-in-Residence at the Montana Institute of Fine Arts, sponsored by a Ford Foundation Grant. From 1973 to 1982, he taught part time at the Maryland Institute, College of Art in Baltimore, Maryland.
Dugmore's paintings are in the collections of the Albright-Knox Art Gallery, the Walker Art Center, the Corcoran Gallery of Art, and the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden.
Edward Dugmore died in 1996 in Minneapolis, Minnesota.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and instructor Edward Dugmore measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1937-1993. Found within this small collection are biographical materials, scattered business and financial records, notes, a file concerning the Drake University Summer Session, printed material, and photographs. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence exchanged with art critic Hubert Crehan and artist colleagues including George Abend, Ernie Briggs, Herman Cherry, Lucien Day, Harvey Harris, Reuben Kadish, Mary Fuller McChesney, and Clyfford Still.
Printed materials include clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and press releases. Photographs are of artwork, Dugmore, and colleagues, including Lewin Alcopley, Anne Arnold, Warren Brandt, Ernest Briggs, Herman Cherry, Hubert Crehan, Lucien Day, Rosalyn Drexler, John Grillo, John Hultberg, Reuben Kadish, Aristodemus Kaldis, Kyle Morris, Stephen and Pam Pace, Charles Pollock, Peter Voulkos, and Hugo Weber.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1948-1993 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1943-1992 (Box 1, 2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Business Records, circa 1951-1972 (Box 2; 2 folders)
Series 4: Notes, circa 1969-1980 (Box 2; 1 folder)
Series 5: Drake University Summer Session File, 1972-1973(Box 2; 5 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, circa 1937-1993 (Box 2; 25 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1960-1983 (Box 2; 9 folders)
Abend, George; Arnold, Anne, 1925-; Brandt, Warren, 1918-; Briggs, Ernest, 1923-; Cherry, Herman; Copley, Alfred L.; Crehan, Hubert; Day, Lucien B., 1916-; Drake University; Drexler, Rosalyn; Grillo, John, 1917-; Harris, Harvey, 1915-1999; Hultberg, John, 1922-; Kadish, Reuben, 1913-; Kaldis, Aristodimos, 1899-1979; McChesney, Mary Fuller; Morris, Kyle; Pace, Pam; Pace, Stephen, 1918-; Pollock, Charles C.; Still, Clyfford, 1904-1980; Voulkos, Peter, 1924; Weber, Hugo, 1918-1971; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs
- Biographical Material, 1948-1993; Series 1; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists of a photo identity card and photocopy of a Maestro de Artes en Pintura diploma from the Universidad de Guadalajara, school transcripts, report cards, a declaration of American Artists, and employment records from the University of Minnesota.
  - School Records, 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - Employment Records, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Account, 1993 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1943-1992; Series 2; (Box 1, 2; 1.5 linear feet)
  Correspondence consists primarily of letters exchanged with art critic Hubert Crehan and artist colleagues including George Abend, Ernie Briggs, Herman Cherry, Lucien Day, Harvey Harris, Reuben Kadish, Mary Fuller McChesney, and Clyfford Still. There are scattered letters from Lewin Alcopley, Milton Avery, Leonard Bocour, John Grillo, Philip Guston, Sam Kootz, Kyle Morris, Philip Pavia, and George Rickey. A letter from Edith Dugmore to the H. W. Wilson Publishing Company encloses a photograph of James Rosenquist with Joan Mondale. Correspondence also includes miscellaneous letters from students.
  - Correspondents with Unknown Surnames, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "A-B,", undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "C,", undated; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "D,", undated; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "F-J,", undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "K,", undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "L-R,", undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondents with Surnames "S-Z,", undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1949; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1954; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1955; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956; (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1957; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1976; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1977; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1980; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1984; (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985; (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1986; (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1988; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, undated (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1962-1972 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Students, 1990-1992 (Box 2)
- Personal Business and Financial Records, circa 1951-1972; Series 3; (Box 2; 2 folders)
  Scattered personal business and financial records include receipts, price lists, and letters concerning financial benefits for education.
  - Business and Financial Records, 1951-1972, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Notes, circa 1969-1980; Series 4; (Box 2; 1 folder)
  Miscellaneous notes include lists of students, a list of artist members of an unidentified club, and student comment sheets.
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1969-1980, undated (Box 2)
- Drake University Summer Session File, 1972-1973; Series 5; (Box 2; 5 folders)
  This file contains letters, notes, printed material, and photographs concerning Dugmore's participation as instructor in the Drake University Summer Session art classes in Des Moines, Iowa.
  - Letters, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Notes, undated (Box 2)
  - School Brochures, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Clippings and Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, circa 1972-1973 (Box 2)
- Printed Material, circa 1937-1993, undated; Series 6; (Box 2; 25 folders)
  Printed Material includes clippings, press releases, a prospectus, exhibition announcements and catalogs, calendars of events, brochures, programs, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, 1941-1992; (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, 1954-1991, undated; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Prospectus, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Dugmore, 1940-1993, undated; (11 folders) (Box 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs for Others, 1958-1990, undated (Box 2)
  - Calendars of Events, 1959-1971 (Box 2)
  - Brochures, 1937-1972, undated (Box 2)
  - Programs, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Reproductions of Art Work, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs, 1960-1983, undated; Series 7; (Box 2; 9 folders)
  Photographs are of Dugmore, family members, and colleagues including Lewin Alcopley, Anne Arnold, Warren Brandt, Ernest Briggs, Herman Cherry, Hubert Crehan, Lucien Day, Rosalyn Drexler, John Grillo, John Hultberg, Reuben Kadish, Aristodemus Kaldis, Kyle Morris, Stephen and Pam Pace, Charles Pollock, Peter Voulkos, and Hugo Weber. There are also photographs of art work by Dugmore.
  - Photographs of Dugmore with Family Members, 1978-1983 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Dugmore with Colleagues, 1960-1981; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Art Work, undated; (3 folders) (Box 2)